使い捨てる[つかいすてる]:to use and then throw away, 人工衛星[じんこうえいせい]:man-made satellite
（ナレーション）
使い捨てられた人工衛星
Abandoned artificial satellites.
Tanks jettisoned from shuttles.
シャトル:shuttlecock, 切り離す[きりはなす]:to detach/to decapitate/to cut loose, タンク:tank (of liquid)
シャトルが切り離したタンク
Refuse generated during
space station construction.
ステーション:station, 建造[けんぞう]:building/construction, 廃棄物[はいきぶつ]:waste matter/waste/garbage
ステーション建造時に出た廃棄物
This vast amount of junk floating in space,
space debris, is a very serious threat.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 浮かぶ[うかぶ]:to float|to rise to surface|to come to mind, たくさん:a lot/lots|enough
宇宙に浮かぶ たくさんのゴミ
スペース:space (room, area, outer space), デブリ:debris, 実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being
スペースデブリは
実は とても危険な存在です
This is a story of 2076, a time in which
this space garbage has become a problem.
2076年―
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|, 物語[ものがたり]:tale/story/legend
これは 宇宙のゴミが
問題になった時代の物語
♪～
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
Phase 15
In Her Case...
Medical checkups are only worthwhile when...
健康診断[けんこうしんだん]:physical examination
（ラビィ）
健康診断ってのはな―
毎年[まいとし, まいねん]:every year/yearly/annually, きちんと:properly/accurately|neatly, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||, 価値[かち]:value/worth/merit
毎年きちんと受けてこそ
価値があるんだよ
...you get one every year like clockwork.
Enough, already! I came here
this year, didn't I?
（ハチマキ）
いいじゃねえか―
今年[ことし, こんねん]:this year
今年は来たんだから
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 心境[しんきょう]:mental state, 変化[へんか]:change|variety|inflection|, 変化[へんげ]:shapeshifting (of an animal or spirit)|incarnation|transformation
（フィー）
どういう心境の変化？
Why the sudden
change of heart?
入社[にゅうしゃ]:joining a company/getting a job with a company/entering a company, 以来[いらい]:since/henceforth, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.)
入社以来 ずっと来なかったのに
You haven't come for a checkup since
the one you had when you were hired.
そりゃあ:very/extremely|that is
（ハチマキ）えっ そりゃあ…
Um...
Because an astronaut has to
take good care of himself!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot, 健康[けんこう]:health/sound/wholesome, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect)
（タナベ）宇宙飛行士にとって
健康は大事ですから
Right, Senpai?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
ねっ 先輩
Yeah. Right.
お… おう
健康[けんこう]:health/sound/wholesome, 一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace
（課長）
そうそう 人間健康が一番だよ
Right! A person's most precious
posession is his health!
Let's all get our checkups together
every year from now on, okay?
毎年[まいとし, まいねん]:every year/yearly/annually, 全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||
これからも
毎年 全員で受けようね
All of us, huh?
全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew
全員ねえ
Edel-san isn't here, though...
さんがい:the three realms of existence|the whole universe (of a billion worlds) that Buddha enlightened, さんがい:third floor
でも エーデルさんがいませんけど
Oh, that's because she's
a contract worker.
契約社員[けいやくしゃいん]:contract employee
（課長）
あっ エーちゃんは 契約社員だから
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 健康診断[けんこうしんだん]:physical examination, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||, 正社員[せいしゃいん]:regular employee/permanent employee/full-time employee
（ラビィ）そう 会社で健康診断を
受けられるのは 正社員だけ
Right, only regular employees get medical checkups.
Oh, okay.
几帳面[きちょうめん]:methodical/punctual/steady
（タナベ）そうか あの几帳面な
エーデルさんが―
I thought it was strange that someone
as punctual as Edel-san would play hooky.
サボり:skipping out/cutting class/truancy, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
サボりなんて
おかしいと思いました
I've never seen her
show up late for work.
遅刻[ちこく]:lateness/late coming
（ハチマキ）あいつが遅刻すんの
見たことねえしな
She's never late submitting
her paperwork, either.
提出[ていしゅつ]:to present/to submit (e.g. a report or a thesis)|presentation, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, 遅らせる[おくらせる]:to delay/to postpone/to put off
（ユーリ）
提出物も遅らせたことない
That girl really has
her act together.
きっちり:exactly/precisely|closely
（課長）
きっちりしてるよね 彼女
Don't you think she's a bit too tightly wound?
She could stand to loosen up a little.
きっちり:exactly/precisely|closely
けど
きっちりしすぎじゃないですか？
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 潤い[うるおい]:moisture|richness|financial leeway|
もう少し潤いってもんが
Yeah, I've never seen
her smile, either.
ニコリ:smile sweetly/smile/grin, ともし:light/lamp|baiting deer with a lighted torch
ニコリともしねえもんな
Now that you mention it,
it's hard to imagine Edel-san laughing.
笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|, 想像[そうぞう]:imagination/guess
そういえば エーデルさんが
笑ったとこって想像できませんね
You're the members of Debris Section, correct?
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||
（エーデル）
デブリ課の方ですね
受付[うけつけ]:reception (desk)/information desk|receipt, どうぞ:please/kindly|by all means
へっ？
（エーデル）受付のほうへどうぞ
Please follow me
to the reception desk.
（ラビィ）あれ？
What the...?
What are you doing, E-chan?
（課長）
何やってんの？ エーちゃん
There will be six
of you, then?
よろしい:good/OK/all right
（エーデル）６名でよろしいですね
あの… どうして
Um, what are you...
I work here part-time
twice a month.
回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||, アルバイト:part-time job/side job
（エーデル）月に２回だけ
ここでアルバイトをしてるんです
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 受け付け[うけつけ]:reception (desk)/information desk|receipt, 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|, いただける:to be able to receive/to be able to take|to be able to eat
それより 早く受け付けを
済ませていただけませんか？
Anyway, could we please get you
checked in as quickly as possible?
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, バイト:work (esp. part time or casual)
次のバイトが入っていますので
I have another job
after this.
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), もやう:to co-operate (in enterprises)/to hold in common/to share, もやう:to moor (a boat)
えっ 他にもやってるんですか？
なんで そんなに…
You have another job besides this one?
Why do you have so many?
It doesn't conflict with my
contracted work hours at Technora.
契約[けいやく]:contract/compact/agreement, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
今は テクノーラとの
契約時間ではありません
This way, please.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), どうぞ:please/kindly|by all means
では こちらにどうぞ
はあ…
The deal will be made here at Seven.
This trio came up here yesterday.
取り引き[とりひき]:transactions/dealings/business, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, セブン:seven
（ギガルト）
取り引き場所は このセブンだ
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 組[くみ]:set (of items)|group (of people)|typesetting, 上がる[あがる]:to rise|to enter (esp. from outdoors)|to enter (a school)||
（ギガルト）
昨日 ３人組が上がってきている
Geez, these guys keep coming up
here into space to make their deals.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
（隊員）
たく… 次から次へと宇宙に来て
Seven is under INTO law, so even if they get
caught, the punishment will be less severe.
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 法[ほう]:law|method|mood|, 適用[てきよう]:applying (e.g. a technology)/adoption, セブン:seven
（ハキム）
連合法が適用されるセブンじゃ―
捕らえる[とらえる]:to catch|to grasp (e.g. meaning)|to captivate, 刑[けい]:penalty/sentence/punishment, 軽い[かるい, かろい]:light (i.e. not heavy)|light (i.e. of foot)|non-serious||
捕らえても刑が軽いからな
Hakim, it's not our place to decide what their punishment will be.
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 刑[けい]:penalty/sentence/punishment, 与える[あたえる]:to give (esp. to someone of lower status)|to provide|to assign||, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
（ギガルト）
ハキム どんな刑を与えるかは
俺たちの仕事じゃない
Yes, sir.
（ハキム）はい
We'll arrest them while they're
making the deal. That is our...
取り引き[とりひき]:transactions/dealings/business, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 押さえる[おさえる]:to pin something down|to seize|to gain control of something|
取り引き場所を押さえるぞ
それが俺たちの… んがっ
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
（ハキム）せ… 先生！
（ギガルト）ううっ うっ…
Sensei?
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
（ハキム）ギガルト先生！
（ギガルト）ぐぐぐ…
Gigalt Sensei!
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
救安を呼べ！ 早く！
Call a medical team!
Hurry!
Yes, sir!
おやじ:first character (of a dictionary entry), おやじ:one's father/old man/one's boss
（隊員）はい おやじさん！
Old man!
くううっ…
Earrings!
ピアス:earrings (for pierced ears), 似合う[にあう]:to suit/to match/to become
（タナベ）
ピアス… は似合わないかな
Might not look good
on me...
Still, it's our first date,
so why not?
せっかく:stone burial chamber, せっかく:with trouble/at great pains|rare, デート:date/go on a date
でも せっかくのデートだしな
Yuri-san, how much longer are you
going to look after this sea cucumber?
ナマコ:sea cucumber (Holothuroidea spp.), 預かる[あずかる]:to look after|to take charge of|to reserve (judgment)
（エーデル）ユーリさん ナマコは
いつまで預かるのですか？
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 頂き物[いただきもの]:(received) present/gift
ああ それ
第３事業部からの頂き物だから
Oh, that was a gift
from Third Division.
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 飼う[かう]:to keep (a pet or other animal)/to raise/to have
（タナベ）あっ すいません
私がペットとして飼いますから
Oh, I'm sorry,
I'm going to keep it as a pet.
An animal like this?
生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal
（エーデル）この生き物をですか？
Right.
（タナベ）はい
Oh, I see.
（エーデル）そうですか
In that case, please file a personal
effects registration form.
私物[しぶつ]:private property/personal effects, 登録[とうろく]:registration/accession/register, 届け出[とどけで]:report/notification, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
では 私物登録の
届け出をお願いします
Okay.
（タナベ）はーい
たまに:occasionally/once in a while, ピアス:earrings (for pierced ears)
うん たまにはピアスとかも
Maybe it'd be nice to wear
earrings for a change...
Those are for Lingum piercings.
（エーデル）それ リンガムですよ
（タナベ）え？
えっ リンガムって？
Lingum? What's that?
It's a tongue piercing.
They go through the underside of the tongue.
舌[した]:tongue|tongue-like object/clapper (of a bell), ピアス:earrings (for pierced ears)
舌にするピアス
舌[した]:tongue|tongue-like object/clapper (of a bell), 裏側[うらがわ]:the reverse/other side/lining, えぐる:to gouge/to hollow out|to greatly perturb, 通す[とおす]:to stick through|to spread throughout|to make a path between two points||
舌の裏側に
えぐるように通すんです
ええっ そうなの
Really?
ええ？
I don't think they would
look good on you.
似合う[にあう]:to suit/to match/to become
似合わないと思いますよ
（タナベ）えっ？
ピアス:earrings (for pierced ears)
ピアス
Earrings.
You don't?
そうですか？
似合う[にあう]:to suit/to match/to become
ええ 似合わないと思います
あなたには
No, I don't.
They wouldn't suit you at all.
（タナベ）んんん…
Hey, which do you think
would look better?
なあなあ:colluding/complicity/liaison, どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives)
（ハチマキ）
なあなあ どっちがいいと思う？
右[みぎ]:right/right hand side|afore-mentioned (esp. in vertical Japanese writing)
（トモルド）右かな
The right one, I guess.
But if you wear that, you'll want something
on your neck. Like a choker or something.
首[くび, クビ]:neck|head|dismissal, 首[しゅきゅう, しるし]:decapitated head of an enemy, ポイント:point, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
でも それだったら
首にポイントが欲しいな
チョーカー:choker (type of necklace)
チョーカーとか
I don't have
a damn choker.
持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
そんなの持ってねえよ
貸す[かす]:to lend/to loan|to rent out
お前 貸してくれよ
Let me borrow one!
持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
俺も持ってないって
I don't have one, either.
おーい:hey!/oi!|I
おっ おーい チェンシン
Hey! Cheng-Shin!
用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|
（チェンシン）ん？ 何か用かい？
Need something?
You have a choker, right? Let Hachi borrow it.
チョーカー:choker (type of necklace), 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
お前さ チョーカー持ってたよな
（ハチマキ）ああっ
貸す[かす]:to lend/to loan|to rent out
ハチに貸してやってくんねえか
（ハチマキ）ああっ
- T-That's okay!
いいんだよ そんなの
持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
おっ 何 持ってんだよ チェンシン
What's that you
have there, Cheng-Shin?
Oh, that's the pamphlet
for the Jupiter project.
木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), 計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule, パンフレット:brochure/pamphlet
（チェンシン）
ああ 木星計画のパンフレット
I hear they're going to put out a call for Von Braun crew applicants inside the company.
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 乗組員[のりくみいん]:crew, 社内[しゃない]:within a company/in-house, 公募[こうぼ]:public appeal (e.g. for contributions)/public offering (of securities)/public advertisement (of a post), らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
フォン･ブラウン号の乗組員
社内公募するらしいから
You're gonna apply?
申し込む[もうしこむ]:to apply for/to make an application/to propose (marriage)
申し込むのか？
Yes, but the competition is probably going to be tough.
競争率[きょうそうりつ]:ratio of successful (applicants) to total applicants, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive
（チェンシン）
競争率は高いだろうけどね
How about you, Hachi? It sounds exciting.
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
ハチはどうする？ 面白そうだよ
俺か？ 俺は…
Who, me?
Well, I...
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||
ああっ… 無理 無理
Nah, it's hopeless! They're just gonna pick
people from Control and Astrogation, right?
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 航宙[こうちゅう]:space flight, 決まり[きまり]:rule|settlement|habit||
どうせ
管制課か航宙課で決まりだろ？
They'll show me the door once
they hear I'm from Half Section.
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 門前払い[もんぜんばらい]:turning another away at the gate or front door/refusing to receive a caller
半課じゃ 門前払いさ
Hey, that's right! You always talked about wanting to be the captain of the Von Braun, didn't ya?
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman
そっかあ フォン･ブラウンの
船長になりたいって―
前から言ってたもんな
Give 'em hell, Cheng-Shin!
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
頑張れよ チェンシン
（チェンシン）ああ？
あっ タナベ君？
Who, Tanabe-kun?
She's taking a personal
day today.
有休[ゆうきゅう]:paid vacation/paid holiday, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
（ラビィ）今日は有休を取ってるよ
Today is the deadline for her to renew her EVA license.
船外[せんがい]:outboard/extra-vehicular, 作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing, 免許[めんきょ]:license/permit/licence, 更新[こうしん]:renewal/update/innovation, 締め切り[しめきり]:deadline|cofferdam|closed (door, window, etc.)
船外作業免許の更新
今日が締め切りなんですが
And I don't think she's handed in her registration for the sea cucumber yet, either.
ナマコ:sea cucumber (Holothuroidea spp.), 私物[しぶつ]:private property/personal effects, 登録[とうろく]:registration/accession/register, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
ナマコの私物登録も
まだみたいですし
Being one day late
is no big deal.
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 遅れる[おくれる]:to be late/to be delayed/to fall behind schedule
まあ いいじゃない
１日くらい遅れたって
If a temp worker like me put off doing
her job, I'd be in breach of contract!
派遣[はけん]:dispatch/despatch|temporary employee (esp. from an agency), 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 遅らせる[おくらせる]:to delay/to postpone/to put off, 契約[けいやく]:contract/compact/agreement, 違反[いはん]:violation/offense/offence, 違反[いへん]:breaking (a contract, promise, etc.)
派遣の私が仕事を遅らせたら
契約違反になるんです
Please don't assume that I'm like an official
employee like you are, Assistant Manager.
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance, 一緒にする[いっしょにする]:to unite/to join|to confuse with, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
社員の係長補佐と
一緒にしないでください
Hey, I have a lot
going on right now.
いろいろ:various|various colors (colours)
私だって いろいろあるんだよ
And anyway, I'm your superior.
No, you could even say I'm your employer.
大体[だいたい]:outline|general|in the first place, 上司[じょうし]:superior authorities/boss, 雇い主[やといぬし, こしゅ]:employer, とも言う[ともいう]:also called
大体 僕は君の上司
いや 雇い主とも言えるんだよ
But forget about that.
This thing is harder than it looks.
大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||
そんなことより
これ 思ったより大変でさ
何か いいコツ 知らない？
Do you know any good tips
for playing it?
ん？
Mail?
メール:email, アドレス:address
（エーデル）
メール？ このアドレス…
Wait, this address is...
Sasha?!
サーシャ
（ハチマキ）んっ…
んっ… あ…
Say something, damn it.
話せる[はなせる]:to be able to speak/to be able to talk|to be understanding
何か話せよ
何かって？
Like what?
Like anything.
何でもいい
Well, how long have you
had feelings for me, Senpai?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
じゃあ 先輩は―
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
いつから
私のこと好きだったんですか？
聞くか そういうこと
What kind of question
is that?!
You told me to say "anything,"
didn't you?
何でもいいって
言ったじゃないですか
How about you?
お前はどうなんだよ
Who, me?
私ですか？
I think it was...
私は…
Maybe it was when I first
went out into space with you.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
私は
先輩と初めて宇宙に出たときかも
Oh. No kidding...
ああ そう
Now it's your turn, Senpai.
I told you, so now you go!
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint
次 先輩の番ですよ
私 言ったんですから
あっ 俺は…
Well, I...
ああっ… 俺は…
I guess it was...
（チェンシン）ハチ？
（ハチマキ）あっ…
Hachi?
（タナベ）チェンシンさん
Cheng-Shin-san?!
Um, we were just... That is, we...
（ハチマキ）
ああ いや あの… これは その…
How's it look?
どうだ？
（女性隊員）２人だけ
I only see two.
この男が来ていません
This man isn't here.
He stayed in
the hotel, huh?
ホテル:hotel, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
（ハキム）ホテルに残ったか
What should we do?
（女性隊員）どうします？
Hugo is over at the hotel. We'll stick to
the plan and stake out the restaurant.
ホテル:hotel
ホテルはフムが行ってる
我々[われわれ]:we, 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, どおり:in accordance with/following|roughly, 店内[てんない]:store interior, 張る[はる]:to stick|to stretch|to form (e.g. ice on a pond)||, 張る[ばる]:to be prominently .../to be persistently ...
我々は予定どおり 店内で張るぞ
Hakim!
ハキム
（ハキム）ん？
How's Old Man Gigalt doing?
おやじ:first character (of a dictionary entry), おやじ:one's father/old man/one's boss
ギガルトのおやじさんは？
They took him
to the hospital.
病院[びょういん]:hospital, 運ぶ[はこぶ]:to carry|to come|to wield (a tool, etc.)|
病院に運んだ
Oh.
そう
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
ギガルト先生のことだ
This is Gigalt Sensei
we're talking about.
我々[われわれ]:we, 任務[にんむ]:duty/function/office, 終える[おえる]:to finish|to graduate, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
我々が
任務を終えて戻るころには… ん？
By the time we have this mission
wrapped up, he'll probably...
Hoshino?
知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance
星野(ほしの)…
（女性隊員）知り合い？
You know that man?
Yeah.
作戦[さくせん]:tactics/strategy|military or naval operations, 変更[へんこう]:change/modification/alteration
（ハキム）ああ 作戦変更だ
Okay, change in plans.
We'll let Ron's team handle the restaurant.
店内[てんない]:store interior, チーム:team, 任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
店内は ロンのチームに任せる
I'm a real bastard...
最低[さいてい]:least|worst|awful|
（ハチマキ）
その… 最低だよな 俺って
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
お前の気持ち 知ってたのに
I knew how you felt,
but I lied to you.
うそをつく:to tell a lie/to fib
俺は うそをついてたんだ
I never meant to lie to you or
to myself about how I felt, but I...
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
チェンシンにも 自分の気持ちにも
うそをつく:to tell a lie/to fib
うそをつくつもりは
なかったんだけど…
言い訳[いいわけ]:excuse|explanation
いや 言い訳だよな
No, I'm just
making excuses.
From your point of view,
it's a simple case of betrayal.
裏切り[うらぎり]:treachery/betrayal/perfidy
その… チェンシンから見れば
ただの裏切りだし―
Go ahead and hit me or kick me. I deserve it!
殴る[なぐる]:to strike/to hit/to beat, 蹴る[ける]:to kick|to refuse/to reject
殴るなり蹴るなり
お前のしたいようにしてくれ
Deep down, I guess I knew.
（チェンシン）
分かってたよ 何となく
えっ？
She'd been turning me
down lately.
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 断る[ことわる]:to refuse|to inform|to ask leave, ばっかり:only/merely|approximately
最近 断られてばっかりだったし
I'm sorry.
（タナベ）すみません
Cheng-Shin, I...
（ハチマキ）チェンシン 俺…
気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry
気にするなよ ハチ
Don't worry about it, Hachi.
It's not like Tanabe-san and I were married or anything.
結婚[けっこん]:marriage
別に 俺とタナベさんは
結婚してたわけじゃないし―
I don't think I have a claim on her
just because we slept together once.
権利[けんり]:right/privilege, 主張[しゅちょう]:claim/insistence/assertion, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
権利を主張しようなんて
思わないさ
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
一度 寝たくらいで
（ハチマキ）いっ
（タナベ）えっ？
そ… そうだよな
Y-Yeah, I guess not... It's not like we're
grade schoolers or something.
中学生[ちゅうがくせい]:junior high school student/middle school pupil, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
中学生とかじゃあるまいし
そのくらい…
That doesn't mean...
We did no such thing! Cheng-Shin!
（タナベ）
違いますよ！ チェンシンさん
Sorry, sorry... I'm just kidding, Hachi.
冗談[じょうだん, ぎだん]:jest/joke/funny story
ごめん ごめん 冗談だよ ハチ
えっ
Tanabe-san and I never
even kissed.
キスもしてないよ タナベさんとは
うん
性格[せいかく]:character/personality/disposition, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（ハチマキ）お前 性格 悪いぞ
You have a warped personality,
you know that?
ささやか:meagre/meager/modest, 復讐[ふくしゅう]:revenge
（チェンシン）ささやかな復讐さ
Call it a little payback.
You can allow me that much, right?
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
それくらい 許されるだろ？
Good work, Dolf-kun.
疲れ[つかれ]:tiredness/fatigue
（専務）ドルフ君 お疲れ
Second Division was the clear leader
again this quarter.
今期[こんき]:the present term, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 一人勝ち[ひとりがち]:being the sole winner|winner-take-all
今期も第２事業部の
一人勝ちだねえ
Thank you, sir.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
（ドルフ）ありがとうございます
What do you say? Would you care
to join me for a drink later?
つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other
（専務）どうだ？ よかったら
このあと つきあわないか？
I'm sorry, sir, but I've
already made plans.
申し訳[もうしわけ]:apology/excuse, 先約[せんやく]:previous engagement/prior contract
申し訳ありません
先約がありますので
はあ… ふん
Turning down an invitation from the
Executive Vice President like that...
専務[せんむ]:special duty/being in sole charge of a duty|senior managing director, 誘い[さそい, いざない]:invitation/introduction|temptation, 断る[ことわる]:to refuse|to inform|to ask leave, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（ノーマン）
専務の誘いを断るなんて―
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
何様のつもりなんでしょうね
Who does he think
he is?
The next Executive Vice President, possibly.
未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come, 専務[せんむ]:special duty/being in sole charge of a duty|senior managing director, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
未来の専務様… かもしれんな
なっ…
Assistant Chief, would you mind
if I took the afternoon off?
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance, 午後[ごご]:afternoon/p.m., 休み[やすみ]:rest|vacation|dormancy (of a silkworm prior to moulting), 頂ける[いただける]:to be able to receive|to be able to eat|to be acceptable
課長補佐 午後から
お休みを頂けませんか？
えっ？
Even contract workers are
entitled to paid time off.
契約社員[けいやくしゃいん]:contract employee, 有休[ゆうきゅう]:paid vacation/paid holiday, 認める[したためる]:to write up, 認める[みとめる]:to recognize|to deem|to approve||
（エーデル）契約社員でも
有休は認められているはずです
With the supervisor's consent,
of course.
担当者[たんとうしゃ]:person in charge (of an area of work, but not necessarily supervising other staff)/person responsible/one in charge, 承諾[しょうだく]:consent/acquiescence/agreement
担当者の承諾が
Sure, that's okay. We'll pretend
that you were here working.
出勤[しゅっきん]:attendance (at work)/being at work/presence (in the office), 扱い[あつかい]:treatment/service
いいよ いいよ
出勤扱いにしとくから
え？
いつも よくやってくれてるし―
You always do such great work here. Besides, everybody is taking the day off, anyway.
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 休む[やすむ]:to be absent|to rest|to go to bed|
どうせ今日は みんな休みだしさ
You don't have to be so formal
about everything, E-chan.
堅苦しい[かたくるしい, かたぐるしい]:formal/strict/ceremonious, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
エーちゃんも
そんな堅苦しく考えないでさ
Just make up the hours
by the end of the month.
月末[げつまつ, つきずえ]:end of the month, 帳尻[ちょうじり]:closing part of a balance sheet/balance of accounts, 合わす[あわす]:to match (rhythm, speed, etc.)|to join together|to face||
月末までに
帳尻合わしてくれればいいから
Okay?
ねえ？
休み[やすみ]:rest|vacation|dormancy (of a silkworm prior to moulting)
（エーデル）
いえ 休みは休みですから
No, sir.
Time off
is time off.
（サーシャ）ああ… ん…
Man, that Cheng-Shin sure has
a mean streak, doesn't he?
結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, 意地[いじ]:stubbornness|disposition|appetite, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（ハチマキ）チェンシンのやつも
結構 意地が悪いよな
So, what do you
want to do now?
（タナベ）
…で これから どうしましょうか？
あの… 八郎太(はちろうた)さん
Um... Hachirota-san?
変[へん]:strange|unexpected|change||
はあっ 今 何か言ったか？
お前 変なこと
Did you say something just now? Something weird?
ハチマキ:headband, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
だって いつまでも
“ハチマキ先輩”じゃ…
Well, I can't keep calling you
Hachimaki Senpai, can I?
No! Absolutely not!
Just call me Hachimaki!
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 呼び方[よびかた]:way of calling, ハチマキ:headband
駄目！ その呼び方 駄目！
“ハチマキ”でいい
But if we're going out...
つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other
でも つきあってるのに…
You call me by my name,
so I should also...
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
私のことも
名前で呼んでくれたって
- Tanabe?
（シャポウ）タナベ？
（タナベ）えっ へっ？
You have the
day off, too?
休み[やすみ]:rest|vacation|dormancy (of a silkworm prior to moulting)
（ヴァンリ）タナベも休みか？
How do you do? I'm Chapeau,
I joined at the same time as Tanabe.
はじめる:to start/to begin|to open (e.g. a store), 同期[どうき]:same period|same year (of graduation, entering a company, etc.)|synchronization
（シャポウ）はじめまして
タナベと同期のシャポウです
Um... I'm Hoshino. I work at
Debris Section with Tanabe-san.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
あっ タナベさんと同じ
デブリ課の星野です
星野？
Hoshino?
ひょっと:possibly/perhaps|unintentionally, おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin
ひょっとして おむつ男？
（ヴァンリ）あっ
Wait a minute... Diaper Man?!
ああっ ご… ごめんね
シャポウ ヴァンリ
Um, I'm sorry, Chapeau, Vanli.
We're in a bit of a hurry.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
私たち 急ぐから
（ハチマキ）うあっ
Hey! Tanabe! Introduce us, darn it!
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 紹介[しょうかい]:introduction/presentation/referral, なさる:to do
ちょっと タナベ
ちゃんと紹介しなさいよー
知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance, ばっか:only/merely|approximately
ハァ… なんだって
知り合いばっかなんだよ
Geez, why do we keep
running into people we know?
It can't be helped.
しかたない:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use
しかたないですよ
This promenade is the only
place on Seven where people can go for fun.
セブン:seven, 遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 通り[とおり]:avenue|coming and going|flow (of water, air, etc.)||, 通り[どおり]:in accordance with|roughly|Street
セブンで遊べる所って
この通りだけですもん
What do people usually do
at times like this?
みんな
こういうとき どうしてんだ？
How about going aboard Toy Box?
If we go there, nobody...
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals
ToyBox(トイボックス)の中とかどうでしょう
あそこなら
That's where we work.
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
あそこは仕事する所だ
It wouldn't feel
much like a date there, you know?
デート:date/go on a date, 気がする[きがする]:to have a certain mood or feeling/to have a hunch
それじゃあ
デートって気がしねえだろ？
（タナベ）フッ
Isn't there anywhere else?
どっか なかったかなあ ああ…
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
（リュシー）
何やってんの？ こんな所で
What are you two
doing here?
Lucie!
知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance
（タナベ）リュシー
（ハチマキ）また知り合いだよ
Here we go again...
（リュシー）バカね
You two sillies. Seven has its own little rules for dating.
セブン:seven, デート:date/go on a date, しかた:way/method/means, ものがある:sentence-ending expression of strong judgement
セブンには セブンの
デートのしかたってものがあるのよ
Um, isn't this a...
（タナベ）あのさ ここって…
Yep. Seven's only establishment for overnight lodgings.
セブン:seven, 唯一[ゆいいつ, ゆいつ]:only/sole/unique, 宿泊施設[しゅくはくしせつ]:accommodations/lodging facilities/boarding house
（リュシー）
うん セブン唯一の宿泊施設
Hotel Spica.
ホテル:hotel, スピカ:Spica (star in the constellation Virgo)/Alpha Virginis
ホテル スピカよ
ホテル:hotel
（タナベ）ホテル！？
（ハチマキ）うっ
A hotel?!
What are you
shouting for?
大声[おおごえ, たいせい]:loud voice
（リュシー）何 大声 出してんのよ
B-But it's a...
（タナベ）だ… だって
泊まる[とまる]:to stay at (e.g. hotel)|to be docked/to be berthed
（リュシー）
やだ 別に 泊まるわけじゃないわよ
Oh, come on, it's not like you're going
to stay here overnight or anything.
You get the room for a few hours, and
you watch a movie or eat or whatever.
部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable, 借りる[かりる]:to borrow/to have a loan|to rent, 映画[えいが]:movie/film, 食事[しょくじ]:meal|to eat
時間で部屋 借りて
映画 見たり 食事したりするの
There's no other way to be all by
yourselves on Seven, you know?
セブン:seven
そうじゃないと セブンでは
２人きりになれないでしょ？
なるほど:I see/That's right!/Indeed
なるほど
Oh, I get it...
Everybody does it.
みんな そうしてるわ
Of course, you could always
spend the night, too.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, そのまま:without change/as it is|just like, 泊まる[とまる]:to stay at (e.g. hotel)|to be docked/to be berthed
もちろん
そのまま泊まってもいいけど？
えっ いや あの…
俺はそんなこと あ… あの
Um, I wouldn't... That is, I... Um...
Look at you, getting
all flustered!
ウフフ:giggle/chuckle/titter
（リュシー）
何 テレてんのよ ウフフ
受注[じゅちゅう]:accepting an order/receiving an order/orders received, 経験[けいけん]:experience, 企業[きぎょう]:enterprise/undertaking/corporation
（クレア）
受注経験のある企業は―
The firms that we've ordered from in the past
are on the list I gave you the other day.
先日[せんじつ]:the other day/a few days ago, 渡す[わたす]:to ferry across (e.g. a river)|to lay across|to hand over, リスト:list, とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light)
先日お渡しした
リストのとおりです
This is a list of companies
that have just been added.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 新規[しんき]:new|new item (e.g. customer, regulation)|new customer, 参入[さんにゅう]:entering (the marketplace)/introducing (something) to the market|visiting a high-class or noble individual, 企業[きぎょう]:enterprise/undertaking/corporation, リスト:list
こちらは
新規参入企業のリストです
I guess I'll go ahead
and take it.
一応[いちおう]:more or less|tentatively|just in case|, 頂く[いただく]:to receive|to eat|to be crowned with||
（男性）ああ
一応 頂いておきましょうかね
They're all companies in
developing countries, right?
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 発展[はってん]:development|expansion|playing around, 途上国[とじょうこく]:developing country, 企業[きぎょう]:enterprise/undertaking/corporation, ばかり:only/merely|approximately
どうせ
発展途上国の企業ばかりでしょ？
発注[はっちゅう]:ordering (materials)/placing an order/order
発注はありえませんが
We'll never place any orders with them.
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 絡み[からみ]:linkage/entanglement/involvement, 絡み[がらみ]:about/concerning/related to, 最優先[さいゆうせん]:maximum preference/maximum priority/priority handling
（男性）では
フォン･ブラウン絡みは最優先で
Well, give top priority to any work
related to the Von Braun.
（クレア）分かりました
Understood, sir.
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 事業[じぎょう, ことわざ]:project/enterprise|act, 先進国[せんしんこく]:advanced (developed) country/advanced nations, クラブ:nightclub, クラブ:club/fraternity/sorority, 持ち回り[もちまわり]:rotation/by turns
連合の事業は
先進国クラブで持ち回り
INTO's business only goes to
members of the First World club.
いつものことだけど
I guess that
never changes.
ハチ
Hachi?
Wow! This room
is pretty big!
結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, 広い[ひろい]:spacious/vast/wide
（タナベ）
へえ 結構 広いんですねえ
A projection TV, too!
You can watch movies and things on this!
プロジェクター:projector
あっ プロジェクター
映画[えいが]:movie/film
これで映画とか見るんだ
うわっ…
Wow! This potted plant is real!
告白[こくはく]:confession|profession of love|confession of sins (e.g. the confessional), もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
（ハチマキ）俺はタナベに告白して
ＯＫもらったわけだし
- I told Tanabe how I feel, and she's okay with it...
大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult
キスもしたし 大人なんだし
And we've kissed... And we're both adults, too...
I-I guess that just about covers everything
as etiquette for this kinda thing goes...
普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, 礼儀[れいぎ]:manners/courtesy/etiquette
あ… ありだよな 普通
礼儀としても
Look at this, Senpai!
It's a balloon-style rescue ball!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 風船[ふうせん]:balloon (esp. small, toy variety), 式[しき]:equation|ceremony|style|, 救命[きゅうめい]:lifesaving, ボール:ball
先輩 ほら 風船式の救命ボール
小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny
こんなに小さくて…
Look at how small it is!
うわあっ
（ハチマキ）ああっ
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）すみません 先輩
I-I'm sorry, Senpai...
はっ…
Tanabe, I...
タナベ 俺…
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
ああっ 先輩！
Senpai!
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
ああっ 悪い 俺…
I'm sorry, I didn't mean...
No, not that! There's someone here!
違うんです 誰かいます
ベッド:bed, 陰[いん]:yin (i.e. the negative)|unseen location (i.e. somewhere private), 陰[かげ]:shade/shadow|other side
何！？
（タナベ）ベッドの陰
What?
Behind the bed!
誰かいるのか？
いるなら出てこい！
Is anybody there?!
If you're back there, come on out!
泥棒[どろぼう]:thief/burglar/robber, 痴漢[ちかん]:masher/molester/pervert, 警察[けいさつ]:police|police officer|police station, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
泥棒か？ 痴漢か？
警察 呼ぶぞ！
Are you a thief? A pervert?!
I'm gonna call the cops!
W-Wait, don't!
You don't need to worry about me.
（サーシャ）ま… 待ってくれ
怪しい[あやしい]:suspicious/dubious|charming
怪しい者じゃない
How much more suspicious can you get?!
You were hiding behind our bed!
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 隠れる[かくれる]:to hide/to be hidden/to conceal oneself
そんな所に隠れてたくせに
何言ってんだ！
Well, I had
a good reason...
ちょいと:just a minute/short time|somewhat, 訳あり[わけあり]:(having) special circumstances (e.g. problems, issues, advantages, flaws, defects, etc.)
（サーシャ）
それが ちょいと訳ありで
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 訳[わけ]:conclusion from reasoning, judgement or calculation based on something read or heard/reason/cause, 訳[やく]:translation/version (e.g. "English version")
どんな訳だよ
Yeah, like what?
話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
話すと長くなるんだが―
Well, it's a long story.
To sum it up
in one word, it'd be "love," I guess.
ひと言[ひとこと, いちげん]:single word/a few words/brief comment, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
ひと言で言うなら“愛”かな
Love?
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
愛？
はあ？
It was love at first sight. We were
drawn to each other like magnets.
一瞬[いっしゅん]:instant/moment/for an instant, 恋に落ちる[こいにおちる]:to fall in love
（サーシャ）
俺たちは一瞬で恋に落ちて―
磁石[じしゃく, じせき]:magnet|compass, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 愛し合う[あいしあう]:to love one another/to be affectionate towards each other|to have sex
磁石みたいに愛し合った
I proposed to her just two weeks
after we met.
出会う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy), プロポーズ:(marriage) proposal, たった:only/merely/but, 週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of)
出会ってからプロポーズまで
たった２週間だったけど―
But we packed more living
into those two weeks...
腐れる[くされる]:to spoil/to rot/to corrode, 役人[やくにん]:government official, 一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 輝く[かがやく]:to shine/to glitter/to sparkle, 週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of)
腐れ役人どもの一生より
ずっと輝いた２週間だったよ
...than a lousy government official
experiences in a whole lifetime.
After I proposed, I went to ask
her parents for approval.
両親[りょうしん, ふたおや]:parents/both parents, 結婚を許す[けっこんをゆるす]:to give permission to marry, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
それから俺は 彼女の両親に
結婚を許してもらいに行った
I was even wearing a suit, which is
totally out of character for me.
柄[え]:handle/grip|stalk (of a mushroom, leaf, etc.), 柄[がら]:pattern|body build|essential qualities|, スーツ:suit, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, 着る[きる]:to wear (in modern Japanese, from the shoulders down)/to put on|to bear (guilt, etc.)
柄にもなく
スーツなんか着ちゃってさ
But I was turned down.
追い返す[おいかえす]:to turn away/to send away
けど追い返された
Why?
どうして？
"We can't give our daughter
to a foreigner," they said.
外国人[がいこくじん]:foreigner/foreign citizen/foreign national, 娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman)
外国人に娘はやれないってさ
But I refused to give up,
and I went to their house again.
諦める[あきらめる]:to give up/to abandon (hope, plans)/to resign oneself (to), きれる:to break/to snap|to be injured, きれる:to be able to wear/to fit into, 一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 訪ねる[たずねる]:to visit/to call on/to pay a visit to
それでも諦めきれなくて
もう一度 家を訪ねたら―
But they had already sent her away
to a place I could never reach her.
届く[とどく]:to reach|to be attentive|to be delivered, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 移す[うつす]:to change|to change the object of one's interest or focus|to spend or take time||
彼女は もう俺の手の届かない所へ
移されちまってた
届く[とどく]:to reach|to be attentive|to be delivered, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
手の届かない所って？
Where you could never
reach her?
Into space, huh?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
宇宙か？
（サーシャ）うん
セブン:seven
セブンにいるんですか？ その人
Is she on Seven? Is that where she is?!
そういうこと
That's right. And I made arrangements
to meet her here in this room today.
部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
それで今日 彼女と この部屋で
会うことになってるんだ
部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable
なんで この部屋なんだよ
Why this room?
I wrote down
the wrong number.
書き間違える[かきまちがえる]:to write incorrectly (e.g. character)/to make a mistake in writing
いや 書き間違えちゃって
I meant to write room 25,
but I put down 35 instead.
号室[ごうしつ]:suffix for room numbers, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
25号室って書くつもりが
35号室って
♪～
Old man! You've got a visitor!
客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest
（社員）おっさん 客だ
Who is it?
どなた:who?
（チャド）どなたですか？
ローン:loan, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
（社員）さあ…
ローン会社のやつとかじゃないの？
Beats me. He looks like he's from
a loan company or something.
久しぶり[ひさしぶり]:a long time (since the last time)/it's been a while (since I last saw, mailed, etc., you)
久しぶりだな
It's been
a long time.
Dolf!
ドルフ！？
We're short on flight directors over
in Second Division. How about it?
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, フライト:flight, ディレクター:director, 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
第２事業部で
フライトディレクターが足りない
どうだ？
Who, me?
俺を？
Third Division doesn't know how
to make the best use of their people.
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 使い方[つかいかた]:way to use something/treatment/management (of help), 下手[したて, したで]:humble position/inferior|underarm grip on opponent's belt, 下手[しもて]:lower part/foot|left part of the stage (audience's or camera's POV)
第３事業部は
人の使い方が下手だな
You're no accountant, Chad.
チャド:Chad, 経理[けいり]:management/accounting, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
チャドに経理なんて
できるわけがない
You're not cut out for it.
Thanks for the vote
of confidence.
（チャド）言ってくれるな
It's an accurate judgment.
正確[せいかく]:accurate/punctual/exact, 判断[はんだん]:judgment|divination|judgement
正確な判断だ
That's one thing about you
that will never change.
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
変わらないな
ほんと:truth/reality|proper, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
お前のそういうところ
ほんと変わらないよ
Not in a million years.
I worked myself half to death
these past five years.
気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
（サーシャ）
この５年 死ぬ気で頑張ってさ
And now I finally have
a restaurant of my own.
ようやく:finally/at last|barely, ようやく:summary/digest, 店[みせ]:store/shop/establishment, 店[てん]:-store/-shop, 持てる[もてる]:to be able to possess (hold, get, etc.)|to be well liked|to endure (the tests of time, the elements, etc.)||
ようやく店を持てたんだ
小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, 味[あじ]:flavor|charm|experience|, 味[み]:(sense of) taste|counter for food, drink, medicine, etc., 抜群[ばつぐん, バツグン]:preeminence/distinction|outstanding
小さいけど味は抜群
It's small, but our food
is second to none.
If you're ever
down on Earth...
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 降りる[おりる]:to descend (e.g. a mountain)|to alight (e.g. from bus)|to step down||, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
あんたらも
地球(オカ)に降りることがあったら…
She's here!
（タナベ）来た！
（ハチマキ）んっ 何だ？
What're you doing?
Sasha-san?
（タナベ）サーシャさん？
I'm scared of
seeing her again...
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid, 顔を合わせる[かおをあわせる]:to meet/to face someone
（サーシャ）
怖いんだ 顔を合わせるのが
I can understand! It's been
five whole years!
（タナベ）
分かります ５年ぶりですもんね
I'm sorry, could you
get the door for me?
開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened
（サーシャ）すまない
開けてやってくれないか？
Sure.
ほんと:truth/reality|proper
（タナベ）はい
（サーシャ）すまないな ほんとに
I'm really sorry.
どうぞ:please/kindly|by all means
（タナベ）どうぞ
Please, come in.
あっ…
エーデルさん！？
Edel-san?
What are you...
どうして…
雰囲気[ふんいき, ふいんき]:mood|a certain air|air, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
よう エーデル
なんか雰囲気 変わったな
Hey, Edel. You seem different somehow.
（ハチマキ）えっ！？
You mean Edel-san is the old girlfriend
that you were telling us about?!
恋人[こいびと]:lover/sweetheart
（タナベ）サーシャさんの恋人って
エーデルさんだったんですか？
（クレア）ハァ…
あっ…
Hey, aren't those guys
with the OSA?
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 保安庁[ほあんちょう]:National Security Board (1952-1954)
（男性１）おい あいつら
軌道保安庁じゃないか？
Oh, hell!
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
（男性２）マズい
（男性１）くそ
Crap!
Come along quietly!
抵抗[ていこう]:resistance|reluctance|resistance||, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（隊員）抵抗はやめろ！
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, うるさい:noisy/loud|annoying
（男性２）うるさい！ お前 来い！
Screw you!
You! Come with us!
（ハキム）ううーっ
（クレア）
うっ ああっ うっ うう…
銃[じゅう]:gun/rifle/small arms, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
（隊員）
銃を持ってるぞ！
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender
（ハキム）うっ
（男性２）ぐおっ…
ああ…
Are you all right?
大丈夫ですか？
はっ… ハキム･アシュミード
Hakim Ashmead?
（ハキム）よく会いますね
We keep running
into each other.
隊長[たいちょう]:commanding officer, 無事[ぶじ]:safety/peace/quietness
（隊員）隊長 ご無事ですか？
Commander,
are you okay?
Yeah. How's it look over at the hotel?
ホテル:hotel
（ハキム）
ああ ホテルのほうはどうだ？
That man named Sasha should still be there.
残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
まだ サーシャという男が
残っているはずだが
号室[ごうしつ]:suffix for room numbers
（隊員）
それが 25号室には誰もいないと
They said that no one
was in room 25.
うん？
What an amazing coincidence!
偶然[ぐうぜん]:coincidence|by chance|contingency (philosophy)
（タナベ）すっごい偶然ですよね
Admittedly, there aren't a lot
of people on Seven...
そりゃ:very/extremely|that is, セブン:seven, 少ない[すくない]:few/a little/scarce
そりゃ セブンは
人 少ないですけど
黙る[だまる]:to be silent
ちょっと黙ってて
Be quiet for a minute.
What did you come here for, Sasha?
何しに来たの？ サーシャ
I came to see you.
君に会いに来たのさ
Sasha-san here has his own restaurant now.
He said he worked himself to death for you.
お店[おたな]:merchant's home (esp. used by apprentices, etc.)|(your) rental home, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
サーシャさん
お店 持ったんですよ
必死[ひっし]:frantic|inevitable death|brinkmate (inevitable checkmate), 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place, たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
エーデルさんのために
必死で頑張ったって
It's small, but the
food is...
小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, 味[あじ]:flavor|charm|experience|, 味[み]:(sense of) taste|counter for food, drink, medicine, etc., 抜群[ばつぐん, バツグン]:preeminence/distinction|outstanding
小さいけど 味は抜群の…
- You're still using that "cook on the outskirts of town" con?
場末[ばすえ]:outskirts (of a town)/run-down district
また 場末のコックネタ？
（タナベ）えっ？
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|
エーデル 少しは笑ってくれよ
How about a little smile for me, Edel?
It's been five years, so don't be so cold.
５年ぶりだってのに つれねえなあ
It hasn't been five years.
It's been four years, eight months.
か月[かげつ]:months (period of)
（エーデル）５年じゃないわ
４年と８か月ぶりよ
ああ？
I've been counting the days. Counting them off
until I've been away from you for five years.
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 数える[かぞえる]:to count/to enumerate
ずっと数えてた
別れる[わかれる]:to part (usu. of people)|to separate (of a couple)|to lose (e.g. one's mother)
あんたと別れて ５年がたつのをね
Edel-san?
エーデルさん？
年間[ねんかん]:years (period of), 別居[べっきょ]:separation/living apart, 続く[つづく]:to continue|to continue (without a break)|to occur again and again||, 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.), 同意[どうい]:agreement/consent|same meaning, 離婚[りこん]:divorce
５年間 別居が続けば
相手の同意なしで離婚できる
If I stay separated from you
for five years,
...I can get a divorce with
or without your consent.
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
（エーデル）えっ？
（ハチマキ）どういうことだよ
What are you
talking about?
This slime used to be
my husband.
夫[つま]:wife|my dear|garnish (esp. one served with sashimi)|, 夫[おっと]:husband
（エーデル）
こいつは私の夫だった男よ
夫[つま]:wife|my dear|garnish (esp. one served with sashimi)|, 夫[おっと]:husband
（ハチマキ）夫！？
（タナベ）でも―
Husband?!
But he said that he proposed,
but your parents were against it.
プロポーズ:(marriage) proposal, 両親[りょうしん, ふたおや]:parents/both parents, 反対[はんたい]:opposition/resistance|reverse
プロポーズしたけど
ご両親に反対されたって
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
変わってないのね
You never change, do you?
Always making up lies on the spot...
場[ば]:place|field|occasion||, 場[じょう]:place/spot/grounds, 限り[かぎり]:limit|degree|as far as possible||, 限り[きり]:end|bounds|delivery date (of a futures contract)||, 涙[なみだ, なだ]:tear/tears|sympathy, 頂戴[ちょうだい]:receiving|eating|please, 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 文[ふみ]:letter/writings, 文[ぶん]:sentence|composition|the literary arts (as opposed to the military arts), 芝居[しばい]:play/drama
その場限りのうそ
お涙頂戴の三文芝居
Cheap sob stories
to milk people for sympathy!
Don't be that way, baby...
I came all
the way here, so come back to...
わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
そう言うなよ
わざわざ こんな所まで来たんだ
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
また俺と一緒に…
働く[はたらく]:to work|to function|to commit (e.g. a crime)|, 遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys, 暮らす[くらす]:to live/to get along|to spend (time)
（エーデル）
また 私にだけ働かせて
遊んで暮らしたいってこと？
You want to force me to work
while you screw around, is that it?
（タナベ）あっ あの…
Um...
I was always picked
by the worst johns...
ひどい:cruel/heartless|violent, 客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest, ばかり:only/merely|approximately, 取[とり]:taking|last performer of the day (usu. the star performer)|active partner (e.g. in judo demonstration)|, 取[どり]:samurai receiving this much rice as a fee|offering of rice cake containing this much rice|person receiving this amount of money as a salary
（エーデル）
ひどい客ばかり取らされたわ
They used handcuffs and collars! Electric shocks!
手錠[てじょう]:handcuffs/manacles, 首輪[くびわ]:(animal) collar|necklace/choker, 電気[でんき]:electricity|(electric) light, ショック:shock (psychological)
手錠に首輪 電気ショック
They made me get piercings
all over!
体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, ピアス:earrings (for pierced ears)
体中にピアスまでされて！
Piercings?
ピアス:earrings (for pierced ears)
ピアスって…
And if I refused,
they beat me!
拒む[こばむ]:to refuse/to reject/to decline, 暴力[ぼうりょく]:violence/mayhem, 振るう[ふるう]:to swing|to exercise (e.g. power, ability)|to flourish
私が拒むと暴力を振るった
You call yourself
a husband?!
夫[つま]:wife|my dear|garnish (esp. one served with sashimi)|, 夫[おっと]:husband
何が夫よ
"'Til death do us part"? "I love you"?
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 愛する[あいする]:to love
“死ぬまで一緒 愛してるよ”
They're just empty words,
you good for nothing pimp!
薄っぺら[うすっぺら]:very thin/flimsy/cheap, 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech, 口先[くちさき]:lip service/mere words|lips
薄っぺらな言葉だけで
口先だけの このヒモが！
わっ エーデル
Edel!
ワイヤ:wire, アンカー:anchor (of a ship), 射出[しゃしゅつ]:shooting/emitting/injecting, 機[はた]:loom
ワイヤアンカーの射出機よ
This is a wire anchor launcher.
They use these to fire ropes into ship hulls.
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 外板[がいはん]:panels, planks or plating on the hull of a ship or aircraft, ロープ:rope, ぶち込む[ぶちこむ]:to throw|to hit|to fire into (e.g. a crowd)|
宇宙船の外板に
ロープをぶち込むやつ
H-Hey, now, if you use
that on a person...
（サーシャ）お… おい
そんなもん 人に使ったら
（エーデル）死ぬわね
They'll die.
C'mon, cut it out, Edel. Okay?
なあ よせよ エーデル なあ
親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), 金[おうごん, こがね]:gold, 金[かね, かな]:money|metal, 学[がく]:-ology/-ics|learning
親もない 金もない 学もない
We've got no parents,
no money, and no education.
For people like us, that was the
only way we could survive.
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, しかたない:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use
そんな俺たちが生きてくためには
しかたなかったんだよ
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
あんたって 少しも変わらない
You haven't changed
one bit.
You keep making excuses so
you won't even have to try.
努力[どりょく]:great effort/exertion/endeavour, 言い訳[いいわけ]:excuse|explanation, ばかり:only/merely|approximately
いつも そうやって
努力しないための言い訳ばかり
ぐっ…
As for me, I have a job.
働く[はたらく]:to work|to function|to commit (e.g. a crime)|
（エーデル）私 働いてるの
ええっ？
Every morning, I go to the office, sit at my desk,
do my job, and go home at night.
毎朝[まいあさ, まいちょう]:every morning, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 机[つくえ, つき]:desk, 座る[すわる]:to sit|to assume (a position)|to hold steady, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 夕方[ゆうがた]:evening/dusk, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
毎朝 会社に行って
机に座って仕事して 夕方には帰る
学校[がっこう]:school, お金[おかね]:money, 稼ぐ[かせぐ]:to earn (income)|to score (points, victory)|to work hard (at one's job), 空く[すく]:to become less crowded/to thin out|to be hungry, 空く[あく]:to open (e.g. doors)|to open (e.g. business, etc.)|to be empty||, バイト:work (esp. part time or casual), 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
学校のお金を稼ぐために
空いた時間にバイトも入れて
I even work part-time jobs in my free time
to earn money for school.
そりゃ:very/extremely|that is, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
何だ？ そりゃ お前らしくもない
That doesn't sound like
the Edel I know.
一生懸命[いっしょうけんめい]:very hard/with utmost effort/with all one's might, 勉強[べんきょう]:study|diligence|discount
私 バカだったけど
でも 一生懸命 勉強してるの
I used to be a fool,
but I'm studying hard.
派遣[はけん]:dispatch/despatch|temporary employee (esp. from an agency), 絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 正社員[せいしゃいん]:regular employee/permanent employee/full-time employee, みせる:to show/to display
今は派遣だけど
絶対 必ず正社員になってみせる
I'm just a temp staffer now,
...but I'm
going to be a full employee one day!
そいつ:he/she|that, 下ろす[おろす]:to take down (e.g. flag)|to drop off (a passenger from a vehicle)|to withdraw money from an account||
分かった
分かったから そいつを下ろせ
- All right.
I understand. Just put that thing down...
愛する[あいする]:to love
俺は お前を愛してるんだ
I love you, baby...
You've got to
be kidding me.
ふざける:to joke/to jest|to make fun of
ふざけるな
I'll make you go away.
And you won't come back.
消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear, 汚点[おてん]:stain/blot/flaw
もう消えちまえ 私の汚点
（サーシャ）ううっ…
Tanabe!
タナベ！
Move!
嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant
どいて
（タナベ）嫌です！
I won't!
A man like him
isn't worth saving!
救う[すくう]:to rescue from/to help out of/to save, 価値[かち]:value/worth/merit
そんな男 救う価値はない！
助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
この人を助けたいんじゃありません
He isn't the one that I want to save.
I don't want you to shoot him!
撃つ[うつ]:to shoot (at)|to attack/to defeat
エーデルさんに
撃たせたくないんです！
（エーデル）はっ
We need you
at the office!
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 役に立つ[やくにたつ]:to be helpful/to be useful
（タナベ）エーデルさんは
すごく役に立ってます
You're more useful than the Chief or Lavie-san, and way more useful than someone like me!
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.)
課長よりも ラビィさんよりも
私なんかよりも ずっと
（サーシャ）んん…
（タナベ）こんな人のために
Don't throw it all away
because of him!
（サーシャ）ううっ
（エーデル･タナベ）うっ
（エーデル）ううっ…
（サーシャ）ヘヘッ
（エーデル）サーシャ！
Sasha!
おごる:to give (someone) a treat|to be extravagant/to live luxuriously, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
たく… 女がおごりやがって
You stupid bitch!
Think you're better than me, huh?
があああっ
（サーシャ）うわっ
ああっ…
（ハチマキ）ううっ…
Let go! Get off of me!
放す[はなす]:to release/to let go|to add (pieces of eggplant, potato, etc.) to water, broth, etc., やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
（サーシャ）放せ 放しやがれ！
- Like hell I will!
（ハチマキ）うるせえ！ この…
ああ… ああっ こら！
Get back here!
Move it!
（サーシャ）どけ！
（タナベ）あっ！
（ハチマキ）待て！
（サーシャ）うわっ うっ
Hold it!
（ハチマキ）待て！
（サーシャ）うわっ うっ
ああっ？
（サーシャ）うおっ うっ…
I'm with the Orbital Security Agency.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 保安庁[ほあんちょう]:National Security Board (1952-1954)
軌道保安庁だ
You will be treated in
accordance with INTO law.
以後[いご]:after this/from now on|thereafter, 処置[しょち]:measure/step|medical treatment, 連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 法[ほう]:law|method|mood|, のっとる:to take over/to capture|to hijack (a vehicle), のっとる:to conform to/to be in accordance with/to follow (rule, tradition, example, etc.), 行う[おこなう]:to perform/to do/to conduct oneself
以後の処置は
連合法にのっとって行われる
You have the right to
contact an attorney.
弁護士[べんごし]:lawyer/attorney, 連絡を取る[れんらくをとる]:to get in touch with, 権利[けんり]:right/privilege
お前には
弁護士と連絡を取る権利―
You have the right
to remain silent.
黙秘[もくひ]:remaining silent/keeping secret, 権利[けんり]:right/privilege, 認める[したためる]:to write up, 認める[みとめる]:to recognize|to deem|to approve||
黙秘する権利が認められている
You're a real go-getter,
aren't you, Hakim?
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 熱心[ねっしん]:zeal/enthusiasm
仕事熱心だな ハキム
I am. Which is why I'm going to get
statements from all of you later.
ああ だから あとで―
事情[じじょう]:circumstances/consideration/conditions, 聴取[ちょうしゅ]:listening/hearing|radio reception, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
君たちにも
事情聴取をさせてもらうよ
回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||
はいはい これで２回目か
Fine, fine... I guess
this is twice now.
You and I must have some
kind of connection, Hoshino.
よくよく:the one after next, よくよく:exceedingly/very, 縁がある[えんがある]:to be fated to/be linked by fate
（ハキム）
よくよく縁があるようだな 星野
Looks that way.
らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
（ハチマキ）らしいな
Edel!
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, チクる:to tattle/to tell on/to inform a superior of someone's actions, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
（サーシャ）エーデル
てめえ チクりやがったな
You ratted me out! Didn't you, you bitch?!
愛する[あいする]:to love
愛してるって言ったのによ
You said you loved me!
Were our marriage vows
nothing but lies?!
誓い[ちかい]:oath/vow, 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech
あの誓いの言葉は
うそだったのかよ
What else are you good for
besides selling your body?!
売る[うる]:to sell, 以外[いがい]:with the exception of/excepting, てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself
女を売る以外
てめえに何ができるんだよ！
Come on, get moving!
とっとと:quickly/at once/right away
（隊員）とっとと来るんだ
Please, Edel! Help me! Edel!
（サーシャ）
エーデル なあ エーデル
助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
助けてくれ エーデル！
Edel-san...
エーデルさん
撃つ[うつ]:to shoot (at)|to attack/to defeat, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
（エーデル）撃つ気はなかった
I wasn't going
to shoot him.
I just wanted to make sure he'd never
come near me again, that's all.
二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), 姿を現す[すがたをあらわす]:to make an appearance/to show up
二度と私の前に
姿を現せないようにしたかっただけ
私は…
Because I...
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 街[がい]:.. street/.. quarter/.. district, 街[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||
私は
ゴミためみたいな あの街には…
I'm never going back to that cesspool
of a town. Or back to that scum.
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
あんなクズのところには
二度と戻らないから
They say that Old Man Gigalt
has stabilized.
おやじ:first character (of a dictionary entry), おやじ:one's father/old man/one's boss, 落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||
おやじさん 落ち着いたようです
That's good.
そうか
レギュラー:regular, シフト:shift, 皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything
（アナウンス）
レギュラーシフトの皆さん―
Members of the regular shift,
good morning.
おはようございます:good morning
おはようございます
It is now 9AM, Greenwich Mean Time.
Technora is now open for business.
Good morning.
おはようございます:good morning
（エーデル）おはようございます
Oh, good morning. You're sure here early.
おはようございます:good morning
（タナベ）
あっ おはようございます
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
早いですね
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday
エーデルさん 昨日は…
Edel-san, about yesterday...
船外[せんがい]:outboard/extra-vehicular, 作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing, 免許[めんきょ]:license/permit/licence, 更新[こうしん]:renewal/update/innovation, 締め切り[しめきり]:deadline|cofferdam|closed (door, window, etc.), 昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday
船外作業免許の更新
締め切りは昨日ですよ
The deadline for your EVA license
renewal was yesterday.
なさる:to do
えっ？ あっ ごめんなさい
I'm sorry!
Um... Where'd I?
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ...
えーっと… あれ？
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 作成[さくせい]:drawing up (e.g. legal document, contract, will, etc.)/preparing/writing, 提出[ていしゅつ]:to present/to submit (e.g. a report or a thesis)|presentation
（エーデル）こちらで作成して
提出しておきました
I filled it out and submitted it
for you.
えっ？ あっ…
I also filed your registration
for the sea cucumber.
ナマコ:sea cucumber (Holothuroidea spp.), 私物[しぶつ]:private property/personal effects, 登録[とうろく]:registration/accession/register
（エーデル）ナマコの私物登録も
しておきましたから
Ah... Thank you, Edel-san.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
あっ ありがとうございます
エーデルさん
（エーデル）フッ…
エーデルでいいよ
You can call me Edel.
♪～
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
Ignition
ハァ…
How did it go, Lavie-chan?
どうだった？
ラビィちゃん
フィー:phi, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances
（ユーリ）
フィー 事故だったんだ
Fee, it was an accident. Don't blame yourself.
責める[せめる]:to condemn|to urge|to torture|
自分を責めるな
うーん:hmm/well
うーん…
I'm no doctor, but I know something
that might do the trick.
医者[いしゃ]:(medical) doctor/physician, 薬[くすり]:medicine|efficacious chemical (gunpowder, pesticide, etc.)|(pottery) glaze|, 薬[やく]:dope/narcotics|medication
俺は医者じゃないが
いい薬がある
Maybe he's...
ひょっと:possibly/perhaps|unintentionally
（ノノ）ひょっとして
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 喪失[そうしつ]:loss/forfeit, 症[しょう]:illness
（医師）空間喪失症
It's Spatial Loss Disorder.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
先輩 地球に戻ったほうが
いいんじゃないですか？
Senpai... Maybe it would be better
if you went back to Earth.
（ハチマキ）あっ…